Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 13 -- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials 1640-1791 Mss.B.F85inventory13
American Philosophical Society
- Miscellaneous Franklin Materials
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1786 October 21; D. 2p.; The Continental Congress
    Printed in the Secret Journals of Congress, I, 268.
  - to [Thomas] Jefferson. Chaillot., 1786 December 22; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Blome, Otto, baron von
    Sending him the box of books which he kindly promised to take charge of, for Dr. Franklin.
  - to The Legislature of Virginia., 1786 December 29; D. 3p.; Simms, Col. Charles
    Memorial in reference to lands bought of Alexander Ross.
  - to Sarah [Franklin] Bache., A.L.S. in 3d P. 1p.; Martin, -----
    Mr. Martin's absence prevents him from waiting on the President [of Pennsylvania].
  - to The House of Assembly of Georgia., L. 2p.; Wayne, General Anthony
    Recommendation of Reverend William Nixon to conduct a Seminary for the education of Youth, accompanied by a copy of a report of the Committee of the Assembly thereon.
  - to Marquis de Castries., 1787 April 25; A.L.S. 3p.; Le Roy, Julien David. Paris
    Sending him a printed copy of Dr. Franklin's letter on maritime matters together with his reply. His plan for the construction of a fast ship to ply between London and Paris; enclosing the list of subscribers; desires to put the Marquis's name at the head of the list.
  - to Samuel Vaughan., 1787 May 20; A.L.S. 4p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Gives Dr. Franklin, Mr. [Richard] Bache and him the power to act as his attorneys in his trouble with Mr. [Samuel] Wharton and Mr. [Francis] Coffyn, and hopes they will soon bring the affairs to a conclusion.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1787 May 29; Mem. 5p.; Memorandum, Philadelphia
    The military districts of the city of Philadelphia and the assignment thereto of the several companies composing the fifth and seventh battalions of the militia.
  - to [William?] Vaughan., 1787 July 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Harrison, William. Ragland
    The man who made Dr. Franklin's bells is Mr. Romley, of Middle Moorefields.
  - to Henry Cuyler., 1787 August 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Bache, Theophylact. New York
    Introducing William Temple Franklin, and Mr. de Chaumont [fils]. They are on a visit to some land they possess in the western country.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1787 August; Mem. 3p.; Dashwood, Francis. Postmaster-General of Jamaica
    Account of his claims upon George Henry, merchant of Philadelphia.
  - to John Lawrence., 1787 September 14; A.L.S. 1p.; Taylor, John. New York
    Desiring to know the cause of the long delay in sending a certain remittance to Governor [William] Franklin.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1787 November 7; D.S. 1p.; Barbé de Marbois, Pierre François. Philadelphia
    Certificate that Barthelemy Terrasson is a French merchant, who has always acknowledged the consular jurisdiction of France and who has a right to all the exemptions granted to French merchants.
  - to Samuel Osgood and Arthur Lee., 1787 December 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Barclay, Thomas. New York
    Concerning the settlement of the accounts between the United States and John Ross.
  - to Capt. Spence., 1788 January 5; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Vaughan, William. Mincing Lane
    Requests him to deliver the box to Dr. Franklin and the parcel, as directed, to Dunlap.
  - to ----- -----., 1788 February 17; A. Dr. of L. 4p.; Franklin, William Temple. Philadelphia
    Replies to enquiries about the manner of living here. Differs greatly in town and country. In large cities a few people live in opulence, the greater number modestly, and very many with the strictest economy. Style of living is generally very simple. People do not consider themselves obliged to make a certain show and appearance, as in Paris. Even people of means do not receive or entertain much here. Women seldom dine out, but give inexpensive tea-parties. Men's style of dress very simple, women's somewhat more costly. Carriages very seldom used. Gives prices of a few commodities, what a house can be rented for, etc.
  - to J. Ross., 1788 March 1; L.S. 1p.; Grand and Cie. Paris
    Announcing a change in their firm.
  - to J. Ross., 1788 March 21; L.S. 2p.; Grand and Cie. Paris
    Concerning a balance due them. Have heard that the Farmers-General have enough tobacco now. Uneasiness created in the business world by the preparations for war against Turkey, by two empires.
  - to ----- de Lassize., 1788 April 16; L. 2p.; Vigny, Saugrain de. Falls of the Ohio.
    Left Paris with a companion and both arrived in good health at Pittsburg. Were delayed there four months owing to the ice on the Ohio river. Left Pittsburg, with three companions, on March 19th. After six days' voyage were attacked and pursued by Indians in a flat boat. Replied to the Indians' fire and killed one. He was wounded in the hand and one of their party killed by the Indians' fire. Tried to escape by swimming towards land. His companion from Paris, M. Picque, was killed by the Indians on reaching the bank. Was himself taken prisoner but escaped by leaping into the river. After several days' wandering in the woods was taken up by a passing boat and reached the Falls of the Ohio safely. Copy of M. Picque's will is appended to the letter.
  - Miscellaneous Papers., 1788 May 10; D.S. 1p.; Marshel, William. Washington Co., Pennsylvania
    Depositions relative to the seizure of a negro boy.
  - David Redick, of the Supreme Executive Council of Pennsylvania., 1788 May 10; A.L.S. 3p.; Addison, Alexander. Washington
    Concerning a certain negro boy, brought into Pennsylvania by David Davis who, after his term of service expired, attempted to put his name on record again as a slave, but finding this impossible, hired him into Virginia.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1788 May 17; D.S. 3p.; Morris, William. Baltimore, Maryland
    Deposition relative to the theft of a horse.
  - to James Bowdoin, 1788 June 28; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Gannett, Caleb. Boston
    The volume of [the American Philosophical Society's] Transactions not yet received, nor is the [American] Academy [of Arts and Sciences] in possession of the French work mentioned; both will be extremely acceptable; Dr. Franklin's generosity.
  - to Lucas Des Peintraux., 1788 July 22; L.S. 1p.; Bache, Benjamin Franklin. Philadelphia
    His Grandfather being ill in bed desires him to reply to his letter, delivered by M. Saugrain. Will be pleased to forward anything he receives from M. des Peintraux.
  - to Francis Hopkinson., 1788 August 17; L. 2p.; -----, -----
    In reference to a meeting at Mess's Tavern [Germantown?] at which was read a circular letter from Cumberland Country, where patriotic meetings are established in all the towns, and these resolved to meet in Harrisburg on the third day of September, as well for Wrath as for conscience sake, to consider amendments to the proposed [National] Government previous to its organization. States that similar letters are sent to all States to ascertain the number of antifederalists, and, if found sufficient, to make effectual opposition and to stand forth boldly in their cause. Is informed that bloody battles seem unavoidable unless speedly counteracted by sufficient authority. Hopes the Council of Pennsylvania will take immediate measures to remove the sinews of war and to seize the insurgents. Informed that Blair McClenachan and Dr. Fraly intend going to different parts of the country to incite the people.
  - to Col. George Morgan, Prospect, New Jersey., 1788 September 16; A.L.S. 3p.; Poellnitz, Friedrich Karl Hans Bruno, Baron von. New York
    Sorry the New Jersey Land Society dissolved the association. Was told by him the last time they met that Dr. Franklin was suffering with the stone. Knows a method of dissolving the stone. Offers to go to Philadelphia to show how to apply this remedy.
  - to David Redick, Philadelphia., 1788 November 19; A.L.S. 1p.; Scott, Thomas. Washington, Penna
    The Trustees of the Academy have a high sense of their obligation to Dr. Franklin not only for his generous donation, but for his recommendation of a tutor in whom they have the highest confidence.
  - to ----- -----., 1788 December; A. Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, William Temple. Philadelphia
    Introducing Mr. Gouverneur Morris.
  - to Robert Hare., 1789 April 15; A.L.S. 1p.; White, Rt. Rev. Dr. William
    Thinks if there be a probability of their inducing any alterations in his proposal, it is best they should have a chance before their meeting.
  - to Comte de Montmorin., 1789 July 21; L.S. 2p.; Ségur, Louis-Philippe, comte de. St. Petersburg
    False reports circulated by the enemies of Rear Admiral [John] Paul Jones about the latter leaving Russia in disgrace. To counteract the effect of these on the public mind in France, would like the enclosed article to be inserted in the "Gazette de France" and other papers. The honors received by Paul Jones from the King of France, his bravery and services rendered to the common cause in the last war and the personal friendship of the writer for his former companion in arms, have impelled him to take lively interest in Rear Admiral Jones during his stay in Russia.
    Copy of the article referred to is appended with note saying it was published in the "Gazette de France." The article states that Rear Admiral Jones, on leaving for France where private affairs required his presence, was received in audience by the Empress of Russia. A brief account is then given of his brilliant part in the American war, his services in Russia and the honors received by him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin Bache., 1789 August 6; L.S. Tho[mas] Willing, Pres[iden]t. 1p.; The Bank of North America. Philadelphia
    Desires him to print a number of tickets of the denomination of 3/90 and 1/90 of a dollar; this step taken for public convenience, at a time when the circulation of copper coin is suspended.
  - to Comte d'Esteins and Chevalier [Jean François] de Burgoing., 1789 August 26; L.S. 2p.; Ségur, Louis-Philippe, comte de. St. Petersburg
    Introducing Rear Admiral [John] Paul Jones. Refers to his services in Russia in the last campaign there, the Order of St. Anne being conferred on him. Relates how he eventually fell into disfavor with the Court of Russia. False reports circulated about his private character by his enemies and rivals. The Empress deceived by these reports and Admiral Jones was forbidden to appear at Court. He alone (Comte de Ségur) defended him and championed his cause and with such effect that Admiral Jones was cleared of the charges made against him and was received in audience by the Empress. Asked leave of absence, on the pretext of attending to some private business in France and Denmark. Real motive of his leaving Russia was resentment he felt against the way he was treated while there. Requests his two friends to render Rear Admiral Jones all the services in their power.
  - to Mrs. [Sarah] Bache, Philadelphia., 1791 May 30; A.L.S. 2p.; Robinson, Debby. Virginia
    There is a certain Mrs. Welsh who claims she is well acquainted with her and that Mr. [Richard] Bache was her guardian. Wishes to be informed if this is true.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1799; Mem. 1p.; Petitions to the Pennsylvania Assembly
    Referred to the Committee on Roads and Inland Navigation.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 1810; Mem. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Relative to the portrait of Dr. Franklin by [David] Martin.
  - to The People of England., L.S., "An English Shepherd." 22p.; Adams, Francis
    Seven letters, to be inserted in the American newspapers, relating to political affairs in England and to the war with America.
  - to Mrs. [Sarah] Bache., A.L.S. 1p.; All, Isaac
    Writes inquiring after the health of her father [Dr. Franklin].
  - Miscellaneous Papers, L. 2p.; "An American."
    Arraignment of those Englishmen who virulently write and talk against America.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 8p.; Andrews, -----
    Owner of the brig "Sally" which was seized as a prize off the coast of Martinique by a French privateer; presents his claim to the Council of Prizes at Paris for the release and return of his vessel.
  - to Mrs. [A. F. Burnett]., A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Bache, Sarah
    Will be extremely happy in seeing her and the rest of her agreeable friends that evening.
  - to ----- -----., A.L.S. 1p.; Bancroft, Edward
    Suggests his procuring a few lines from Dr. Franklin to the Lieutenant of Police, which will obviate the necessity of a passport.
  - to [Gov.] William Franklin., A.L.S. 3p.; Bard, John
    Case of Miss Mary Pinhorn who did not receive her share in the division of the Commons of Bergen. Prays for the appointment of a new Commission to examine her claims.
  - to The Continental Congress., L. 3p.; Barry, Dr. David and Ann Hellier Barry, his wife
    Relative to their claim to certain lands near Wilmington, N.C.
  - to Mrs. [Sarah] Bache., Thursday; A.L.S. 1p.; Burnett, Mrs. A. F
    Was unaware she had been invited to her house for that day. Will dispense with her engagement with Mrs. Morgan, and accept her friendly invitation.
  - to Edward Bancroft., A.L. in 3d P. 2p.; Bousie, Mrs
    As the passport has been sent some time ago to Calais for Captain Meriton, Mrs. Bonsic sends the enclosed letter from Mr. Audibert as a proof that the Court has granted a passport.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, D. 11p.; Bouchet, Captain Pierre
    Report of the shipwreck of his vessel, "Aimable Elizabeth," on a voyage to Philadelphia, and of the rescue of his crew by the ship "Nancy."
  - to [William] Strahan., June 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Bowles, John
    Request him to obtain information from Dr. Franklin, to correct the account of the post. Thinks it is altered since the time of inserting in the map.
    A. E. by Dr. Franklin. In regard to the postal arrangements in the Colonies.
  - to Mme. Brillon, Passy., L. 1p.; Brillon, Mlle
    Was surprised and sorry that Dr. Franklin did not come to the Palace (of Justice). Had secured a seat for him and his grandson. The hearing will be more interesting next Thursday when M. Brillon is to go more thoroughly into the case.
  - to ----- -----., Mem. 3p.; de Basseville, Pierre Buisson
    Account of his services in the navy of France for twenty years.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, 2p.; The Old Hermit of Buxüeil
    On the Americans and their struggle for independence. Deploring the fate of Philadelphia in possession of the English.
  - to ----- -----., L. 3p.; Caffiéri, Jean Jacques
    The dispute between himself and W[illia]m Temple Franklin. Sends all the correspondence in the matter and requests him to communicate it to Mme. -------, so that she may know the truth.
  - to Le Ray de Chaumont., 1p.; de Chaumont, Mme. Le Ray
    With reference to a piano.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 1p.; Chenel, -----
    Certificate of the efficacy of a powder discovered by Jacques Faynard, for stopping hemorrhage.
  - to [Antoine Raymond Jean Gualbert Gabriel] de Sartine., L. 2p.; Coderc, Gabriel-Aphrodise de (Henry's brother)
    Petition.
  - to Comtesse de Bourdie., N. 1p.; Coirard, Jean Jacques
    Requests her to obtain a letter of recommendation for him from Dr. Franklin, to the City authorities of Philadelphia.
  - to The Duke of Chartres., D. 3p.; The First President of the Court of Aids
    Speech praying for intercession with the King, against the levying of further taxes.
  - to Mrs. [Sarah] Bache., A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Coxe, Mr and Mrs
    Regret that they cannot accept her invitation.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Diss. 4p.; Crantz, -----
    Reflections on the aurora borealis.
  - to Benj[amin] Vaughan, London., A.L.S. 1p.; Crawford, Adair, 1748-1795
    Departure of Mr. Redford for Paris, the following morning; if Mr. Vaughan has any commands, desires to have them that evening.
  - to Comte de Vergennes., Mem. 32p.; D'Acosta frères
    Petition relative to their claim against the State of Massachusetts for arms, munitions of war and supplies furnished during the war of Independence.
  - to Comte de Milly, Paris., January 15; N. in 3d P. 1p.; D'Alembert, Jean le Rond
    Recommending a talented man who might be of service to Dr. Franklin.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Verses. 3p.; Alembert, Jean le Rond d', and others
    Translation of the celebrated Latin verse by an unknown author— "Eripuit caelo fulmen, sceptrumque tyrannis" often applied to Franklin. Drinking song in honor of Dr. Franklin by M. D'Alembert.
  - to Jona[than] Williams, [Jr.]., A.L.S. 1p.; Deane, Silas, 1737-1789
    Sends a copy of the order he gave to Mr. Montieu on Mr. [Ferdinand] Grand, and of [Jonathan] Williams [Jr.]'s award, on which it was founded.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Poems. 1p.; "Demophile."
    Impromptu verses ridiculing the eagerness of the people of Paris to see Voltaire. Other verses on Louis XVI and the war with England.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 12p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Remarks on political economy, how taxes should be levied and apportioned; high customs duties illogical and unjust especially to the consumer, ruinous to trade, etc.
    (In French. Incomplete.)
  - to Le Ray de Chaumont., A.L.S.; Fargès, M
    Thanks for sending him the Gazettes.
  - to Mme. [de Chaumont?]., A.L.S. 2p.; Terrasson, Antoine
    His approaching departure for America; desires her to obtain letters of recommendation from Dr. Franklin for himself and his brother, established in Baltimore.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Poems. 3p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Sonnets in imitation of fragments from the Latin poets Lucilius and Ennius. —Reflections on man, his complex nature, etc., after reading Young's "Night Thoughts."
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Verses. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Epigrams, etc., on doctors.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, A. Verses. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Epitaph to "Gros-laid" a tame toad.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Verses. 1p.; Feutry, Aimé Ambroise Joseph
    Advice to the people of Asia and Africa.
  - to Captain [John Paul] Jones., L. 2p.; Sir Robert Finlay, Bordeaux. L'Orient
    Concerning the purchase of hollow bullets, made in Sweden.
  - to ----- -----., A. Dr. of L. 4p.; Fox, George
    Arguments denying that the soul always thinks.
  - to ----- -----., L.S. 1p.; Franklin, William, 1731-1813
    Will have no part in the proposed settlement.
    (First part missing.)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, A. Diss. S. 6p.; Franklin, William Temple
    Exercise in composition, on Friendship.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, A. Mem. 3p.; Franklin, William Temple
    Exercises in French grammar.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple
    Memorandum concerning the treatment of Loan Office bills.
  - to [Charles Biddle]., [1787 November 22?]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple
    Thanks him for his trouble in this business.
  - to [Jacques Alexandre César] Charles., A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple
    Asks leave to bring a few of his friends to hear his discourse and requests him to put his name down as a subscriber for his course of lectures.
  - to ----- -----., A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, William Temple
    With reference to M. [Louis] Anty's claim against a debtor in the United States.
  - to Marquis de Castries., L.S. 4p.; Twenty French Sailors
    Belonged to the crew of the privateer "Benganza," Capt. [Gustavus] Cunningham. Petition for wages and prize-money due to them.
  - to Don Fran[cis]co de Sarratoe., A.L.S. 2p.; de Gamon, Don Miguel Manuel
    Concerning procuring the acquittal of Semencia de los Bostoneses.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 2p.; Gautier, John Guy
    Is a merchant at Barcelona; requests the Masonic Lodge of Patriotism to secure his appointment as Consul for the United States at that port.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Diss. 12p.; Gellée, M
    Remarks on the present state of the Northern parts of Europe. Refers to the powerful alliance which may be formed between Russia and Sweden. Thinks this power will be more exorbitant than that of France and Spain, united in the house of Bourbon. An account of Russia's progress and the conquests she has made. Is using the same politics which made Rome mistress of the world. Cautions Southern Europe against that growing power.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, A. Verses. 1p.; Golowkin, Comtesse de
    Humorous and witty couplets on a certain pleasure resort compared to the Garden of Eden.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin., A.L.S. 1p.; Grace, Sarah R
    Sends thanks for a cloak.
  - to ----- Dalibard., Mem. 2p.; Guérin, -----
    Request him to obtain Dr. Franklin's influence for his son, who wishes to secure orders for shipments of salt to the United States.
  - to ----- Dangeuil., A.N.S. 1p.; Guillard, -----
    Sending a pamphlet and requesting him to read it and hand it to Dr. Franklin.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 1p.; Halley, Dr. Edmund
    Life insurance observations.
  - to Jean Lafitte Cadet., [C. 1780 March 11]; Mem. 1p.; Halstead, John Matthias
    List of Continental Loan Office bills of exchange drawn on the Commissioners at Paris.
  - to The Lords Commissioners for Sick and Hurt Seamen, London., L.S. "Humanitas." 2p.; Hartley, David
    Protest against the ill treatment of American prisoners in England. Makes several charges against Cowdry, the Agent, who has charge of the prisoners, of robbing them, giving them insufficient and tainted rations, depriving them of fresh air, etc. The prisoners who attempt to escape are put into the black hole, upon the floor of which water always lies, and on half-rations upon which it is impossible for them to live.
  - to [Charles Theodore,] Elector Palatine Duke of the Two Bavarias., L. 2p.; Herbegs, John
    Petition of the heir of Jean Striepers concerning his claim to a considerable lot of land in and near the city of Philadelphia.
    (In French. Copy. In duplicate.)
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Diss. 3p.; L'héritier, -----
    An allegorical definition of calumny expressed in eight different languages, to which is appended some Latin verses on the same subject.
  - to [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy., April 30; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; de Claye, Comte D'Héronville
    Begs him to make use of the accompanying packet and to send him as definite a reply as possible.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Printed poems. 11p.; Jarry, -----
    On the birth of the Dauphin. Venus foiled three times. On Marie Antoinette.
  - to [Barbeu] Dubourg., A. L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Rochefoucauld, Louis Alexandre, duc de
    Returns the "Extract des Journaux" and the Minutes or Proceedings of the Pennsylvania Convention. Asks if it would be possible to get a copy of the latter.
  - to Mlle. de Chaumont., L. in 3d P. 1p.; La Salle, M de
    Requests her to read the enclosed letter and make use of the subjoined address, as desired by M. Thirion.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 3p.; Louis XVI, King of France, 1754-1793
    Draft of manifest declaring war against England and promising help to the United States.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, D. 40p.; Louis XVI, King of France, 1754-1793
    Instructions and regulations concerning pupils in the Engineer School, engineers and inspectors of bridges and roads.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, D. 1p.; Minister Luberien, of Germantown, Pennsylvania
    Certificate that Christian Rimshard was lawfully married to Marguerite Geisselin.
  - to ----- Keay., L. in 3d P. 1p.; Marignié, -----
    Requesting him to use his good offices with Dr. Franklin to have his uncle, M. Grangent, appointed Consul for the United States at Cette.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, Mem. 4p.; Marshall, Humphry
    Catalogue of trees, shrubs and plans, native to North America, collected for Mr. [Richard] Bache.
  - Miscellaneous Papers, D. 1p.; The Massachusetts House of Representatives
    Resolve concerning the annual grant to the Governor.
    A. copy by Thomas Cushing.
  - to [Louis Le Veillard]., A.L.S. 1p.; Mayor, -----
    Will send Mr. [William Temple] Franklin's shoes as soon as done.